<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="about_ph_in_philippines"><![CDATA[
        <p>The pH level of coastal waters is an important factor that influences
        the overall health and stability of the marine ecosystem. pH is a measure
        of how acidic or alkaline a solution is and is measured on a scale from 0
        to 14, with 7 being neutral. Values below 7 indicate acidity, while values
        above 7 indicate alkalinity.</p><br/>
        <p>In Manila Bay, average pH of water samples (7.84 ± 0.34) was significantly lower than
        the average pH of Laguna de Bay (8.57) (Sumalapao et. al, 2016)</p><br/>
        <p>A good pH level for coastal waters typically ranges between 7.5 and 8.4,
        which is slightly alkaline to neutral. This range is considered optimal for
        many marine organisms, including fish, shellfish, and various forms of
        marine life. However, different species may have specific pH requirements,
        so slight fluctuations within this range may not significantly impact the
        ecosystem.</p><br/>

<ol type="1">
<li><b>Aquatic Life:</b> Many marine organisms, including fish, corals, and other
aquatic creatures, have specific pH level requirements for survival and growth.
Fluctuations in pH can stress or harm these organisms, disrupting the balance of
the marine ecosystem.<br/></li>

<li><b>Coral Reefs:</b> The Philippines is home to diverse and extensive coral reef
systems. Corals are sensitive to changes in pH; an optimal pH level is crucial
for their growth and calcification. Lower pH levels due to increased acidity in
the water can negatively impact coral health and hinder reef development.<br/></li>

<li><b>Water Quality:</b> pH affects the solubility and availability of nutrients and
minerals in water. An appropriate pH level supports the presence of essential
nutrients needed by marine life. Moreover, it influences the toxicity of certain
substances; variations in pH can alter the toxicity of chemicals, affecting aquatic
organisms differently.<br/></li>

<li><b>Ecosystem Balance:</b> Coastal areas in the Philippines are rich in biodiversity.
The pH level plays a role in maintaining the balance of the entire ecosystem,
including the interactions between different species and their habitats.<br/></li>
</ol>
<br/>
<p>Monitoring and maintaining an optimal pH level in coastal waters through proper
management practices, reducing pollution, and mitigating factors contributing to pH
changes are essential for preserving the health and sustainability of marine
ecosystems in the Philippines.</p>
<br/>
<p>References:<br/>
<small>Sumalapao, D. E., Cruz, L. L., Cua, S., Dauigoy, H. V., & De Leon, E. (2016).
On the pH and Acid Neutralizing Capacity Profile of Manila Bay Coastal Water Samples
in Manila, Philippines. Manila Journal of Science, 9(2), 104-113.</small>
</p>

    ]]>
    </string>


    <string name="about_temperature_in_philippines"><![CDATA[
<p>Temperature in coastal waters is critical for marine life and ecosystem health.
It influences the distribution, behavior, and physiological processes of marine
organisms. Specific species may have temperature preferences within which they
thrive, and fluctuations outside these ranges can stress or harm them.</p><br/>

<p>The weather and climate patterns in the Philippines are significantly influenced
by two main monsoon seasons: the southwest monsoon, prevailing roughly from May
to October, and the northeast monsoon, lasting from November to April.
During these periods, temperatures typically range from <b>21°C</b> to <b>32°C</b>.
Analyzing temperature and precipitation records reveals the country\'s climate
can be categorized into distinct seasons: the rainy season, spanning approximately
from June to November, and the dry season, typically occurring from December to May.
(Szekielda & Guzman, 2021)</p><br/>

<p>Temperature significantly impacts coastal waters in several ways:</p><br/>

<ol type="1">
<li>
<b>Aquatic Life:</b> Temperature plays a critical role in the growth, reproduction, and
behavior of marine organisms. Different species have specific temperature ranges
within which they thrive. Fluctuations in temperature can stress or harm marine life,
 affecting their metabolism, growth rates, and survival.</li>

<li>
<b>Habitat and Ecosystems:</b> Changes in temperature can alter the physical and chemical
properties of coastal waters, influencing the distribution of habitats and ecosystems.
For example, coral reefs are sensitive to temperature changes; increases beyond
certain thresholds can lead to coral bleaching and mortality, impacting the entire
reef ecosystem.</li>

<li>
<b>Ocean Circulation and Currents:</b> Temperature gradients influence ocean currents
and circulation patterns. Variations in coastal water temperature can affect the
movement of currents, which, in turn, impacts nutrient transport, weather patterns,
and the distribution of marine species.</li>

<li>
<b>Chemical and Biological Processes:</b> Temperature influences the solubility of gases
and nutrients in water. Changes in temperature can affect oxygen levels, nutrient
availability, and the rate of biological processes, which can impact the overall
health of coastal ecosystems.</li>
</ol>
<br/>

<p>References:
<br/>
<small>Szekielda, K., & Guzman, J. (2021). Changes in the Philippine Coastal Environment. International Journal of Geology,
Earth & Environmental Sciences, 11(4), 198-207.</small>
</p>
    ]]></string>
</resources>